Lionel Kubwimana

Software Engineer

I am a self-taught Software Engineer passionate about automation. I also have a background as a Network Engineer with 2 years work experience. I am always enthusiastic about writing code to build tools which solve (only) real-world problems through challenging projects.

lionel.kubwimana@gmail.com

+33 6 15 44 29 22

in

www.linkedin.com/in/l-kubwimana

in

www.github.com/LionelKb

()

Work Experience

09/2014 - Present

Paris, France

Network Engineer

Covage

Telco operator specialized in fiber deployment and IP services.

Tasks/Achievements

- Testing, validating and writing technical documentation describing new IP services and solutions to be deployed on the MPLS/FTTH Covage network.
- Product Owner of two in-house projects involving the automation of the network. Responsible of the code, strategy, vision, roadmap and feature definition.
- Level 3 Support Escalation for the Network Operation Center team.

01/2014 - 06/2014

Network Engineer Intern Covage

Tasks/Achievements

- Built Command Line (CLI) tools in a Linux environment.
- Automated the management of the network configurations to be used for a specific customer request. The tool developed generate the needful configurations files for the routers, the switches and the CPEs.
- Built a network configuration audit tool. It checks the incoherences due to manual provisionning of the existing services.
- Studied the needed steps for a migration from Per-Vlan Spanning-Tree to Multiple Spanning-Tree on a part of the aggregation network.

07/2012 - 12/2012

Software Engineer Intern

Covage

Tasks/Achievements

- Built web-based tools running in a Linux-Apache-MySQL-PHP environment.
- Designed a tool used for scheduled planned works on the fibers to identify and inform the customers affected by the fiber cut. It improved the existing process from one working day to 30 minutes.
- Developed an user-friendly interface giving the outline of parts of the network using the Google Maps API and queries to a GIS database containing the entire Covage fiber network.
- Automated the CPE turn-up deployed on the entire network using a DHCP server with a embeded database and an single web page used to register the new equipments to be delivered.

Education

09/2011 - 06/2014

Troyes, France

Network Engineer's Degree

Université de Technologie de Troyes

06/2013 - 12/2013

Singapore

Computer Engineering, Exchange Semester

Nanyang Technological University

09/2009 - 06/2011

Lille, France

Bachelor of Computer Science

Université Lille 1 - Sciences et Technologies

Technical Skills

IP Routing Protocols: BGP, ISIS

Switching: QinQ, Spanning-Tree, EoMPLS
Service Provider Architecture: IP/MPLS, FTTH
Vendors: Cisco, RAD, Redback Ericsson, Calix E7

Scripting: Python, Perl

Linux CLI

Web Development: HTML, CSS, Javascript, PHP, MySQL

Tools: Sublime Text, Git, Trello

Projects

Automated Network Service Provisioning

 Web-based platform used by the delivery team to configure and provision a service without any access to the CLI of the network equipments.

Network Configuration Audit

 Python scripts that check if the configuration of the network equipments is done according to the specifications described by the engineering team.

Soft Skills

Interpersonal Relationships

Intercultural and interreligious awareness and openness aiming for a more united world.

Group Leading

Guiding teenagers to make life decisions and embrace perspectives that build a more fraternal world.

Lifelong Learner

Constantly learning and gaining more knowledge with OpenClassrooms, FreeCodeCamp, Medium, Quora, Memrise, TED Talks, GLS Next, Pocket.

Languages

English

Full professional proficiency

French

Native or Bilingual

Italian

Elementary proficiency

Kirundi

Native or Bilingual

Interests

Reading (Inspirational books) | Music (Guitar & Choir) |
Travelling | Hungarian Language | Sport (Running)